Ou Changkun

Curriculum Vitae

Science and art, life in between

changkun.de 😯 @changkun 😯

Frauenlobstr. 7a

80337 Munich, Germany

**** +49 157 7214 1480 / +86 186 1322 5636

Born on October 25th 1993 in Zhijiang/Hunan/China

People's Republic of China citizenship

Single

Last update: November 25, 2019

Note: colored texts contains clickable URL.

Introduction

Changkun Ou is a research assistant at the University of Munich. His research topics are interdisciplinary in computational geometry, imitation learning, and human-computer interaction. In particular, he would like to leverage three-dimensional polygonal mesh representation learning and visual preference elicitation to develop efficient algorithms or industrial tools for 3D modeling and rendering.

Education

University of Munich (LMU)

Ph.D. Candidate in Media Informatics.

• Publications: Link

University of Munich

Master of Science in Computer Science; GPA: 2.05 in scale of 1.00 (best) to 4.0

University of Munich

Master of Science in Human-Computer Interaction (HCI); GPA: 1.63 in scale of 1.00 (best)

to 5.0, "qut".

• Thesis: Understanding and Predicting Web Browsing Behavior.

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC)

Master of Engineering in Software Engineering

Southwest University for Nationalities (SWUN)

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science; Grade: 3.74 in scale of 4.00 (best) to 1.0, "Top

1 Student".

• Thesis: Designing Alternative Contact-free Control Modalities for Smart Watches.

First Middle School of Zhijiang

Senior Middle School; With university entrance examination (Gaokao)

Changsha Foreign Language School

Senior Middle School

Second Middle School of Zhijiang

Junior Middle School

Chengnan Primary School of Zhijiang

Primary School

Work Experiences

Research Assistant University of Munich

o Teaching Assistant: Online Multimedia

• Teaching Assistant: Seminar Advances in Computer Graphics

o Tutor: Deep Learning and Artificial Intelligence, notes on GitHub

• Tutor: Machine Learning, notes on GitHub.

Munich, Germany

Feb. 2019 - Present

Munich, Germany

Apr. 2018 - Present

Munich, Germany Oct. 2016 - Jan. 2019

Chengdu, China

Chengdu, China

Huaihua, China

Changsha, China

Huaihua, China Sep.2006 - Jul.2009

Huaihua, China

Sep. 2000 - Jul. 2006

Munich, Germany

Aprl. 2018 - Present

Aug. 2016 - Sep. 2016

Sep. 2012 - Jul. 2016

Mar. 2010 - Jul. 2012

Aug. 2009 - Feb. 2010

Page 1 of 5

LabEx Technology Ltd

Chengdu, China Apr. 2018 – Jan. 2019

- o Team leader and leading backend development of the oversea product: I lead and responsible for the product development in backend and frontend. I evolve the existing architecture and split a monolithic backend web application into multiple microservices. The product scales machine cluster from 20 to 200 for active daily users, and its user group increases from 5k to 30k during my incumbency.
- Multi-cloud automation: I developed a fully automated multi-cloud resource management microservice in Go. The service defines a general abstraction cross all cloud provider, it automatically manages all user requested resources allocation and releases outdated resources. For instance, a user of the service can allocate new cloud instances for temporal using without noticing the instance was allocated in either AWS, AlibabaCloud, or others. The service supports more than 15 cloud products and integrated 3 cloud providers, being able to support almost unlimited concurrent users and has been used by 10k+ users.
- o Cluster management service: I developed a microservice in Go that similar to Kubernetes and Docker Swarm. The service manages multiple server clusters, and auto-scaling its cluster size upon request cross multiple cloud providers. Each cluster contains multiple physical machines, and each machine runs many docker containers. The key feature of the service eliminates the difference between the physical machine and the docker container. The runtime of the service includes a system monitor with request prediction algorithm that I invented for efficient auto-scaling with consideration of overcommit ratio and a task scheduler for managing all distributed asynchronous task execution with two-level caching optimization.
- Remote desktop proxy: I developed a middleware that provides generic remote desktop proxy in Go and Cgo. The proxy translates VNC/RDP/SSH protocol data, and establish WebSocket connection to a web browser for providing remote desktop GUI.
- Used tech. stack: Vue, jQuery, Webpack, Electron; Backend: Go, Cgo, Gin, Beego, gRPC, MySQL, MongoDB, Redis, Hypervisor, Nginx, Docker, Kubernetes, AWS, AlibabaCloud, etc.

Fullstack Engineer (Freelance)

Munich, Germany

Rocketlingo UG

Nov. 2017 - Mar. 2018

- Language Teaching Voice Bot: I am part of the team in developing a voice bot that provides English learning teaching service. The bot can communicate with its user and improve their English skill by the real-time response. My responsibility is to implement the backend support designed conversations using Amazon Alexa.
- Speech Recognition Solution & Web Development: I responsible for the development of speech recognition solution over web technologies, such as using WebSocket for audio streaming, using Google Cloud STT and TTS services for speech recognition and synthesis, etc. The challenging part of using existing speech recognition service for a language learning application is a new language learner sometimes does not produces positive audio samples, and even multilingual. Therefore, I developed many text-based falt tolerances technique for improving the understanding of user speech based on machine learning algorithms.
- Used Tech. Stack: Frontend: Angular, Backend: NodeJS, ExpressJS, WebSocket, Python, Flask, MongoDB, Elasticsearch, AWS Serverless, Tensorflow, Numpy, Matplotlib

Shiyanlou

Academic Tutor

Chengdu, China

Software Engineer (Intern)

Jun. 2016 - Sep. 2016

- o Recommendation System: Online course recommendation system; Python; MongoDB; Collaborate Filtering
- o Distributed Log System: Elasticsearch; Logstash; Kibana; Redis
- Cross Platform Desktop Client: Electron based development for macOS/Windows/Linux
- Teaching Meterial Writing: Modern C++ based teaching meterial writing

SWUN Lecture "Human-Computer Interaction"

Chengdu, China

Jul. 2015

Skills

- I have good skills in web development and machine learning. and I can use the following languages: **go**; **python**; **javascript**; **c/c++** (**for optimization**); markdown; IATEX; native Chinese; fluent professional English; elementary German
- Certificates: Coursera, Andrew Ng: Deep Learning Specializations, certificates: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5

Open Source Contribution

- Tensorflow (137k+ stars): Contributor
- Go (65.9k+ stars): Contributor
- etcd (28.2k+ stars): Contributor
- Modern C++ Tutorial (5.1k+ stars): I am the author of the book. The book provides the state-of-the-art content towards modern C++, which includes C++11/14/17/20.
- Go under the hood (1.2k stars): I am the author of the book. The book discusses Go source code, includes its runtime scheduler, garbage collection, compiler and etc.
- Official Tensorflow document translation (3.5k+ stars): I am the main contributor and project maintainer.
- Juejin Translation Public Community (22.6k+ stars): Major contributor, translated 50+ articles. Main reviewer of AI related articles.
- The Swift Programming Language Chinses Translation (18.7k+ stars): Major contributor (in Swift 1.x). The translation was officially acknowledged by Apple Inc.
- occamy: The project implements a modern remote desktop proxy written in Go. It provides web browser GUI for connecting vnc/rdp/ssh servers.
- gomat: The package provides cache-aware lock-free tiling optimization matrix utilities in Go.
- sched: The package for a high performance reliable task scheduling in Go.
- Check my GitHub homepage for more projects: github.com/changkun

Selected Publications

- Changkun Ou, Yifei Zhan, Yaxi Chen. *Identifying Malicious Players in GWAP-based Disaster Monitoring Crowdsourcing System*. In IEEE ICAIBD' 19: Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Big Data. Chengdu, Sichuan, China, May 25-28, 2019. English, Slides.
- Changkun Ou, Jingyi Li, Yong Ma. Cultivation and Incentivization of HCI Research and Community in China: Taxonomy and Social Endorsements. In CHI'19 Workshop on "HCI in China: Research Agenda, Education Curriculum, Industry Partnership, and Communities Building", Glasgow, UK, May 2019, 2019. English, Poster.
- Changkun Ou, Malin Eiband(advisor), Daniel Buschek(co-advisor), Heinrich Hußmann(responsible professor). Understanding and Predicting Web Browsing Behavior. 2019, Master Thesis.
- Changkun Ou. An Introduction to Recent Mobile Affective Inference Techniques: Methods, Applications and Challenges. In Advanced Seminar Media Computer Science, IFI LMU, 2018. English, Slides.
- Matthias Geiger, Changkun Ou, Cedric Quintes. WatchOut: A Road Safety Extension for Pedestrians on a Public Windshield Display. In Lercture Advanced Topics in HCI, IFI LMU, 2017. Arxiv preprint. Poster.
- Changkun Ou, Yaxi Chen(advisor), Andreas Butz(co-reviwer). Designing Alternative Contact-free Control Modalities for Smart Watches. 2016, Bachelor Thesis. Simplified Chinese, English Video
- Yaxi Chen, Changkun Ou. Combining Touch Biometrics and Motion Sensors for Hand Posture Recognition and User Authentication System. In Journal of Southwest University for Nationalities (Nature Science Edition). 2016, 42(4):429-435. Simplified Chinese
- Yaxi Chen, Changkun Ou, Zhaoyang Guo. Space interactions based on monocular vision and simple gestures. In Journal of Southwest University for Nationalities (Natural Science Edition). 2014, 40(16):871-876. Simplified Chinese
- Changkun Ou, Mu Huang, Mengxin Shi, Jiang Cheng. A Study in Keep-Right-Except-To-Pass Rule. In The Mathematical Contest in Modeling, 2014, Meritorious Winner English

Selected Talks

- Changkun Ou. *Understanding Communicating Sequential Processes*. Go Night Reading Meetup, 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. Simplicity is complicated: On the balance of performance and knobs. Internal Doctoral Colloquium Autumn, 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. Real-world Go Concurrency Bugs. Go Night Reading Meetup, 2019. Chinese.
- Changkun Ou. Internals of Channel and Select in Go. Go Night Reading Meetup, 2019. Chinese.
- Changkun Ou. *Identifying Malicious Players in GWAP-based Disaster Monitoring Crowdsourcing System*. ICAIBD 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. A Glimpse to the Advances of Mesh Representation Learning. Internal Doctoral Colloquium Spring 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. *Understanding and Predicting User Browsing Behavior*. Masters Defence Presentation, 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. On the development of Quantified UX Metric. Design Workshop II, IFI LMU, 2018. English.
- Changkun Ou. Capsule Network with Routing Mechanism. Advanced Seminar Deep Learning, IFI LMU, 2018. Part 1, Part 2.
- Changkun Ou. *Understanding Generalization in Deep Learning*. Advanced Seminar Deep Learning, IFI LMU, 2018. English, Video.
- Hermann Redich, Patrick Börzel, Isabella Galter, Collin Leiber, Changkun Ou Convolutional Neural Networks from Zero to Hero. Advanced Seminar Deep Learning, IFI LMU, 2018. English.
- Changkun Ou. Mathematical Modelling Tutorial (Mandarin Chinese). 2016. YouTube Playlist

Open Source Contribution

- Tensorflow (137k+ stars): Contributor
- Go (65.9k+ stars): Contributor
- etcd (28.2k+ stars): Contributor
- Modern C++ Tutorial (5.1k+ stars): I am the author of the book. The book provides the state-of-the-art content towards modern C++, which includes C++11/14/17/20.
- Go under the hood (1.2k stars): I am the author of the book. The book discusses Go source code, includes its runtime scheduler, garbage collection, compiler and etc.
- Official Tensorflow document translation (3.5k+ stars): I am the main contributor and project maintainer.
- Juejin Translation Public Community (22.6k+ stars): Major contributor, translated 50+ articles. Main reviewer of AI related articles.
- The Swift Programming Language Chinses Translation (18.7k+ stars): Major contributor (in Swift 1.x). The translation was officially acknowledged by Apple Inc.
- occamy: The project implements a modern remote desktop proxy written in Go. It provides web browser GUI for connecting vnc/rdp/ssh servers.
- gomat: The package provided cache-aware lock-free tiling optimization matrix utilities in Go.
- sched: The package for a high performance reliable task scheduling in Go.
- Check my GitHub homepage for more projects: github.com/changkun

Public Activities

Presenter
at The ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

Student Volunteer
at Conference Smart Graphics 2015

Guigu Lab Team Leader
at SWUN

Mathematical Modeling Association Academic Vice Director
at SWUN

Clasgow, UK

May. 2019

Chengdu, China
Sep. 2014 - Jun. 2015

Chengdu, China
Oct. 2012 - Jun. 2014

	Chengdu, China Oct. 2012 – Jun. 2014
Honors & Awards	
Siemens AILab Hackathon 2nd Winner	Munich, Germany Nov. 2017
• China National Scholarship $at \ UESTC$	Chengdu, China Sep. 2016
$ \begin{array}{c} \textbf{Excellent Bachelor Graduation Thesis Award} \\ \textbf{at } SWUN \end{array} $	Chengdu, China Jun. 2016
• Best University Graduates Student Award at Sichuan Province	Chengdu, China Jan. 2016
$ \bullet \ \ \begin{array}{l} \textbf{Outstanding Student Scholarship} \\ at \ SWUN \end{array} $	Chengdu, China Nov. 2015
Student Innovative Annual Excellent Project $at \ SWUN$	Chengdu, China Jun. 2015
Sichuan Province Computer Production Competition 2nd Award	Chengdu, China May 2015
• China National Scholarship $at \ SWUN$	Chengdu, China Sep. 2014
American Mathematical Contest in Modeling(MCM) 2014 *Meritorious Winner*	Chengdu, China <i>Apr. 2014</i>

Personal Interests

- Open source contributions: Writting open source book; Contributing and maintaining open source softwares
- Video blogging: Making videos on YouTube channel
- Blogging and knowledge sharing: on https://changkun.de
- Video gaming: Sony Playstation and Nintendo Switch player

References

- Prof. Andreas Butz: currently supervise for Master studies at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Prof. Heinrich Hußmann: exchange student course "Human-Computer Interaction I" at Southwest University for Nationalities, Chengdu, China
- Dr. Daniel Buschek: currently supervise for Master thesis at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Malin Eiband: currently supervise for Master thesis at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Florian Lachner: supervised for individual practical course at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Prof. Yaxi Chen: supervised for bachelor thesis at Southwest University for Nationalities, Chengdu, China
- Prof. Wei Zhou: supervised for bachelor thesis at Southwest University for Nationalities, Chengdu, China